Register of the David Benjamin Bolen Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
David Benjamin Bolen papers
1944-2001
2003C94
Hoover Institution Archives
41 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (18 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, dispatches, memoranda, reports, clippings, and photographs, relating to American relations with South Africa, Botswana, Lesotho, Swaziland and East Germany.
Bolen, David Benjamin, 1923-
Access
Microfilm use only.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (32 reels).
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/ to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1923 Born, Heflin, Louisiana
1948 Member of United States Olympic Team, participates in London games
1950 M.S., University of Colorado
1950-1952 Vice Consul, U.S. Embassy, Monrovia, Liberia
1952-1954 Economic Assistant, U.S. Embassy, Karachi, Pakistan
1955-1958 International Economist, U.S. State Department, Washington, D.C.
1958-1959 Afghanistan Desk Officer, U.S. State Department, Washington, D.C.
1960 M.P.A., Harvard University
1960-1962 Chief of Economic Section, U.S. Embassy, Accra, Ghana
1962-1964 Staff Assistant, Secretary of State for African Affairs, Washington, D.C.
1965-1966 Officer-in-Charge, Nigerian Affairs, U.S. State Department, Washington, D.C.
1967-1972 Economic Counselor, U.S. Embassy, Bonn, West Germany
1972-1974 Economic/Commercial Counselor, U.S. Embassy, Belgrade, Yugoslavia
1974-1976 U.S. Ambassador to Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland
1976-1977 Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Africa, Washington, D.C.
1977-1980 U.S. Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, East Berlin
1981-1989 Associate Director, International Affairs, E.I. du Pont de Nemours and Co.
1989-1994 International business consultant
1997 Distinguished Business Service Award, University of Colorado, Boulder
Scope and Content Note
Acquired in 2003, the David B. Bolen collection in the Hoover Institution Archives documents the long and distinguished career of an American diplomat whose service included ambassadorships in southern Africa and East Germany. The collection consists primarily of official correspondence and reports relating to these and other postings in Bolen's diplomatic career; it also includes materials pertaining to his subsequent work for the E.I. du Pont de Nemours and Co.
The collection has significant materials relating to bilateral diplomacy between the United States and the German Democratic Republic, and to East-West relations in general during the Carter administration, including tensions arising from the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan in 1979. There are reports and official correspondence concerning Bolen's conduct of negotiations leading to a consular agreement between the U.S. and GDR, and numerous documents regarding disputes and incidents stemming from the divided status of Berlin during the latter part of the Cold War. The collection also has extensive materials pertaining to internal developments within the GDR, including the East German government's treatment of dissident artists and writers.
Expanding American exports to East Germany was a high priority of Bolen's ambassadorship, and economic issues figure prominently in the collection as a whole. In particular, there are accounts of American participation in trade fairs in Leipzig. There are also photographs and other materials relating to Bolen's meetings with East German leaders on such occasions, including the head of state, Erich Honecker.
The Bolen collection is equally rich in documentation on political and economic affairs in southern Africa during the 1970s and 1980s. The collection includes correspondence and reports from Bolen's tenure as United States Ambassador to Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland, and extensive materials relating to South Africa from Bolen's career with E.I. du Pont de Nemours and Co. The collection has extensive correspondence and reports on the implementation of the Sullivan principles by foreign companies doing business in South Africa, and on opposition inside that country, and internationally, to the apartheid system.
The collection also contains a selection of speeches and remarks made by Ambassador Bolen over the course of his diplomatic and business careers, most of which deal with African and East German issues. There are also biographical materials, including accounts of Bolen's early prominence as an Olympic athlete. Throughout the collection are interspersed documents that record Bolen's own thoughts on American foreign policy, as well as his views on civil rights and his experiences as a prominent African-American official in the diplomatic service of the United States.
As far as possible, the original arrangement of the collection, as established by Ambassador Bolen, has been preserved.
Africa.; Botswana--Foreign relations--United States.; Botswana.; Diplomats--United States.; Germany (East)--Foreign relations--United States.; Germany.; Lesotho--Foreign relations--United States.; Lesotho.; South Africa--Foreign relations--United States.; South Africa.; Swaziland--Foreign relations--United States.; Swaziland.; United States--Foreign relations--Botswana.; United States--Foreign relations--Germany (East); United States--Foreign relations--Lesotho.; United States--Foreign relations--South Africa.; United States--Foreign relations--Swaziland.; United States--Foreign relations.
- Microfilm Reel Content Guide
  Downloadable PDF file of the Microfilm Reel Content Guide
- Albums,., 1946-2001 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings, correspondence, photographs, programs, reports, and speeches, relating to Bolen's academic, diplomatic, and business careers, as arranged by Bolen
  - No. 1,., 1946-1947 (Folder 1: 1-2)
    Materials relating to Bolen's athletic career, including his participation in track and field events in Greece, Czechoslovakia, and Poland; and clippings and correspondence pertaining to the question of racial discrimination in American universities and in Boulder, Colorado, during the 1940s
  - No. 2,., 1948 (Folder 1: 3)
    Materials relating to Bolen's appearances in the 1948 Olympic Games in London, and in other track and field competitions
  - No. 3,., 1948 (Folder 1: 4)
    Materials relating to Bolen's participation in various track and field competitions
  - No. 4,., 1949-1950 (Folder 1: 5)
    Materials relating to Bolen's participation in international track and field competitions, and to his studies at the University of Colorado. Includes some materials pertaining to his wife, Betty Gayden Bolen, and a copy of a certificate of David B. Bolen's appointment as Vice Consul of the United States in Monrovia, Liberia
  - No. 5-A,., 1950-1959 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Materials relating to Bolen's diplomatic career in the U.S. State Department, including service as an international relations officer attached to the American embassy in Karachi, Pakistan, and as Afghanistan desk officer in the U.S. State Department, Washington, D.C.
  - No. 5-B,., 1957-1963 (Folder 2: 2)
    Materials relating to Bolen's graduate studies in public administration at Harvard University and to his diplomatic career, including service as the economic officer attached to the American embassy in Accra, Ghana. Includes typescript of a speech by Bolen on economic development, Accra, Ghana, 1961 May, and photographs of John F. Kennedy, 1963, and Shirley Temple Black, n.d.
  - No. 5-C,., 1962-1967 (Folder 2: 3)
    Materials relating to Bolen's assignment to duties in the U.S. State Department, Washington, D.C. Includes papers and speeches by Bolen on economic development and minority rights issues, and correspondence regarding the coup d'état in Ghana, 1966
  - No. 5-D,., 1965-1966 (Folder 2: 4)
    Materials relating to Bolen's activities accompanying Assistant Secretary of State, Gov. Mennen Williams, on a diplomatic mission to Africa, 1965. Includes clippings relating to the Vietnam War and American foreign policy
  - No. 31,., 1967-1969 (Folder 3: 1)
    Materials relating to Bolen's service as economic officer attached to the American embassy in Bonn, West Germany. Includes clippings and correspondence pertaining to the George Norlin Award, given to Bolen in 1969 by the Associated Alumni of the University of Colorado
  - No. 33,., 1972 (Folder 3: 2)
    Materials relating to Bolen's activities as economic officer in Bonn, West Germany. Includes one address, "U.S. Interests and Objectives in Western Europe," and several shorter speeches, all delivered by Bolen
  - No. 34,., 1972-1973 (Folder 3: 3)
    Materials relating to Bolen's service as economic officer attached to the American embassy in Belgrade, Yugoslavia. Includes some interpolated personal correspondence, 1990
  - No. 35,., 1973-1974 (Folder 3: 4)
    Materials relating to Bolen's professional activities in Yugoslavia, and concerning his appointment as U.S. Ambassador to Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland. Includes correspondence and reports pertaining to a visit to Yugoslavia by George Shultz, Secretary of the Treasury, 1973
  - No. 5-E (1),., 1974 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    Materials relating to Bolen's tenure as Ambassador to Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland
  - No. 5-E (2),., 1974-1975 (Folder 4: 2)
    Correspondence regarding Bolen's appointment as ambassador, largely from other members of the foreign service of the United States
  - Unnumbered,., 1974-1975 (Folder 4: 3)
  - No. 5-F,., 1975 (Folder 4: 4)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland. Includes clippings and correspondence pertaining to the visit of Rev. Andrew Sullivan to Botswana in 1975, and some interpolated materials pertaining to the application of the Sullivan principles to foreign business activities in South Africa, 1984-1990
  - No. 5-G,., 1974 (Box 5)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland
    - Part one. (Folder 5: 1)
      Includes interpolated clipping, 1979, relating to a 1976 murder case involving William Bradford Bishop, an American diplomat posted to Botswana in the early 1970s
    - Part two (Folder 5: 2)
  - No. 5-H,., 1975-1976
    - Part one. (Folder 5: 3)
      Includes clippings and correspondence relating to the awarding of an honorary degree to Ambassador Bolen from Princeton University
    - Part two. (Folder 5: 4)
      Includes clippings and correspondence relating to the Soweto riots in South Africa
  - No. 5-I,., 1976
    Materials relating to Bolen's appointment as Deputy Assistant Secretary of State, Bureau of African Affairs
    - Part one (Folder 6: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 6: 2)
  - No. 5-J,., 1976
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Deputy Assistant Secretary of State
    - Part one. (Folder 6: 3)
      Includes a speech by Bolen on relations between the United States and Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland, n.d.
    - Part two. (Folder 6: 4)
      Includes correspondence and photographs relating to a visit to Gaborone, Botswana by Sen. Charles M. Percy, and a visit to Africa by Secretary of State Henry Kissinger, with whom Bolen traveled as member of delegation
  - No. 5-K,., 1974 (Box 7)
    - Part one. (Folder 7: 1)
      Includes materials relating to political developments in the Kingdom of Lesotho
    - Part two. (Folder 7: 2)
      Includes printed copy of a speech by Ambassador Bolen, Maseru, Lesotho, 1974 October 7
  - No. 5-L (1),., 1975-1976
    - Part one. (Folder 7: 3)
      Includes typescript of a speech on the media delivered by Ambassador Bolen, Maseru, Lesotho, 1975 June 23
    - Part two. (Folder 7: 4)
      Includes official correspondence relating to the American position vis-à-vis the civil war in Angola
  - No. 5-L (2),., 1974
    - Part one (Folder 7: 5)
    - Part two. (Folder 7: 6)
      Includes typescript of a speech delivered by Ambassador Bolen, Swaziland, 1974 May 17
  - No. 5-M,., 1973-1974 (Box 8)
    Materials relating to Bolen's appointment as Ambassador to Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland
    - Part one (Folder 8: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 8: 2)
  - No. 5-N,., 1974-1975
    - Part one (Folder 8: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 8: 4)
  - No. 23,., 1977
    Materials relating to Bolen's appointment as U.S. Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic
    - Part one (Folder 8: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 8: 6)
  - No. 6,., 1977
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including official correspondence providing Bolen's analyses of political developments in the GDR
    - Part one (Folder 9: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 9: 2)
  - No. 7,., 1977
    Materials relating to Bolen's appointment as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including letters of congratulations
    - Part one (Folder 9: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 9: 4)
  - No. 8,., 1977
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including official correspondence pertaining to his meetings with Erich Honecker and other GDR officials
    - Part one (Folder 9: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 9: 6)
  - No. 9,., 1978 (Box 10)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic
    - Part one. (Folder 10: 1)
      Includes typescript of a speech delivered by Bolen, "US-GDR Relations in a Rapidly Changing World," University of Kentucky, 1978 February 16
    - Part two. (Folder 10: 2)
      Includes correspondence and memoranda relating to a visit to East Berlin by Assistant Secretary of State Patricia M. Derian, 1978 October
  - No. 10,., 1978
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including official correspondence summarizing his meetings with GDR officials
    - Part one (Folder 10: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 10: 4)
  - No. 11,., 1979
    - Part one (Folder 10: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 10: 6)
  - No. 104,., 1978 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, with some interpolated correspondence pertaining to his work for the Du Pont corporation, 1982, and minutes of a meeting of trustees, University of Delaware, 1991
  - No. 12,., 1979 (Folder 11: 2)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, especially concerning negotiations with the East Germans conducted by Deputy Assistant Secretary of State James E. Goodby, Washington, D.C., 1979 May 3-4
  - No. 13,., 1979
    - Part one. (Folder 11: 3)
      Includes clippings and photographs pertaining to a visit to the Leipzig Trade Fair by Erich Honecker
    - Part two. (Folder 11: 4)
      Includes advance copy of a speech delivered by Leonid Brezhnev, East Berlin, 1979 October 6. In Russian, with English translation. Also includes printed copy of a consular convention signed between the United States and East Germany, and typescript of remarks made by Ambassador Bolen at the signing ceremony for this convention, 1979 September 4
  - No. 14,., 1979 (Box 12)
    - Part one. (Folder 12: 1)
      Includes typescript of remarks delivered by Bolen concerning negotiation of a consular convention with the GDR, 1979 May 22
    - Part two. (Folder 12: 2)
      Includes some interpolated correspondence from the University of Kentucky, 1977 October 1
  - No. 15,., 1978-1979
    - Part one. (Folder 12: 3)
      Includes correspondence and photographs relating to a hunting party hosted by Erich Honecker, 1978 December
    - Part two. (Folder 12: 4)
      Includes clippings and correspondence relating to the Leipzig Trade Fair, 1979 March
  - No. 16,., 1979
    - Part one (Folder 12: 5)
    - Part two. (Folder 12: 6)
      Includes some correspondence addressed to Betty Bolen
  - No. 17,., 1979 (Box 13)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including official correspondence regarding political developments in the GDR
    - Part one (Folder 13: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 13: 2)
  - Nos. 19/20,., 1980
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including official correspondence detailing meetings with East German officials
    - Part one. (Folder 13: 3)
      Includes correspondence and memoranda relating to American reaction to the Soviet intervention in Afghanistan and its effect on East-West relations
    - Part two. (Folder 13: 4)
      Includes correspondence relating to Bolen's views on the American boycott of the 1980 Moscow Olympics
  - No. 21,., 1980
    Materials relating to the completion of Bolen's tenure as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic
    - Part one. (Folder 13: 5)
      Includes correspondence pertaining to the American boycott of the 1980 Moscow Olympics
    - Part two. (Folder 13: 6)
      Includes clippings relating to Bolen's farewell meetings with Erich Honecker and other officials of the GDR and the diplomatic corps in East Germany
  - No. 22,., 1977-1979 (Folder 13: 7)
    Official correspondence and reports relating to the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe, and to human rights issues raised by Bolen with the government of the GDR
  - No. 23,., 1977 (Box-folder 14: 1)
    Materials relating to Bolen's appointment as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic
  - No. 24,., 1980 (Folder 14: 2)
    Materials relating to consultations in Washington, D.C., 1980 January 28 - February 1, conducted as part of Bolen's service as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic
  - No. 25,., 1977
    - Part one. (Folder 14: 3)
      Includes clippings and photographs pertaining to Bolen's presentation of his credentials to Erich Honecker, Chairman of the Council of State of the GDR, East Berlin, 1977 August 22
    - Part two (Folder 14: 4)
  - No. 26,., 1978
    - Part one. (Folder 14: 5)
    - Part two. (Folder 14: 6)
      Includes printed transcript of a town hall meeting conducted by President Jimmy Carter, West Berlin, 1978 July 15
  - No. 27,., 1978 (Box 15)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including photographs and correspondence pertaining to various social events hosted by the ambassador and his wife
    - Part one (Folder 15: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 15: 2)
  - No. 28,., 1978
    - Part one. (Folder 15: 3)
    - Part two. (Folder 15: 4)
      Includes typescript of a speech by Oskar Fischer, Foreign Minister of the GDR, 1978 June 6, and official correspondence concerning a Johns Hopkins University study of microwave radiation affecting American embassy personnel in Moscow, 1978 November 22
  - No. 29,., 1978-1980
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including social engagements
    - Part one (Folder 15: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 15: 6)
  - No. 30,., 1978 (Box 16)
    - Part one. (Folder 16: 1)
      Includes photographs and typescript speech concerning the festival, "The American Film Week at Leipzig," 1978 May
    - Part two. (Folder 16: 2)
      Includes news accounts pertaining to a traveling art exhibit from the GDR, "The Splendors of Dresden," 1978 June
  - No. 31,., 1977
    Materials relating to Bolen's appointment as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including letters of congratulation
    - Part one (Folder 16: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 16: 4)
  - No. 36,., 1978-1980
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including official correspondence from the U.S. State Department concerning goals for this posting
    - Part one (Folder 16: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 16: 6)
  - No. 37,., 1978-1979 (Box 17)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including official instructions from the U.S. State Department concerning American goals and objectives vis-à-vis the GDR
    - Part one (Folder 17: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 17: 2)
  - No. 38,., 1978-1979 (Folder 17: 3)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including a discussion paper outlining the American position in advance of a NATO meeting held on 1978 October 2-5, and a cable prepared by Bolen summarizing relations between the U.S. and the GDR, 1980 March 31
  - No. 39,., 1977
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, primarily to negotiations between the U.S. and the GDR regarding a consular convention
    - Part one (Folder 17: 4)
    - Part two (Folder 17: 5)
  - No. 40,., 1977
    - Part one (Folder 17: 6)
    - Part two (Folder 17: 7)
  - No. 41,., 1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, primarily to the signing of a consular convention negotiated between the U.S. and the GDR
    - Part one (Folder 18: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 18: 2)
  - No. 42,., 1977-1979
    - Part one. (Folder 18: 3)
      Includes cable containing a detailed analysis of cultural developments in East Germany, including the activities of dissident writers, 1977 July 15
    - Part two (Folder 18: 4)
  - No. 43,., 1978 (Folder 18: 5)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic. Includes official correspondence relating to the "Splendors of Dresden" touring exhibition of art on loan from the GDR, and a printed copy of a speech by President Carter inaugurating this show's opening in Washington, D.C., 1978 June 1
  - No. 44,., 1977-1979 (Box 19)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic. Includes official correspondence relating to cultural exchanges between the United States and East Germany, including tours of the GDR by American musicians, and a traveling exhibit of photographs from the US
    - Part one (Folder 19: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 19: 2)
  - No. 46,., 1978-1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic. Includes official correspondence relating to dissent in the GDR, and the case of the East German writer, Stefan Heym
    - Part one (Folder 19: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 19: 4)
  - No. 47,., 1978-1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, with an emphasis on cultural and educational exchanges between the United States and the GDR
    - Part one (Folder 19: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 19: 6)
  - No. 48,., 1978-1979 (Box 20)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, especially regarding the resolution of humanitarian cases pending between the United States and the GDR. Includes official correspondence pertaining to divided families and Americans detained in the GDR
    - Part one (Folder 20: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 20: 2)
  - No. 49,., 1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, including official correspondence relating to the granting of travel visas by the GDR authorities
    - Part one (Folder 20: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 20: 4)
  - No. 50,., 1977-1980
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic. Includes official correspondence pertaining to the settlement of Jewish material claims made against East Germany in compensation for property losses suffered under the Nazis
    - Part one. (Folder 20: 5)
      Includes an interpolated letter from Angelika Timm, 1995 March 8
    - Part two (Folder 20: 6)
  - No. 51-A,., 1978-1979 (Box 21)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, with an emphasis on the resolution of humanitarian cases pending between the United States and the GDR. Includes official correspondence pertaining to divided families and American citizens detained in the GDR